So, we know that anxiety runs in families.
Ta biết rằng chứng lo âu là di truyền
If you have a first degree relative with an anxiety disorder, your odds of developing
Nếu bạn có họ hàng gần mắc rối loạn lo âu thì bạn
an anxiety disorder increase compared to the general population.
có khả năng mắc bệnh lớn hơn so với dân số chung
What I want to discuss are some of the common features across anxiety disorders.
Điều tôi muốn nói là về một vài nét chung của các bệnh rối loạn lo âu
Historically, twin studies have indicated that heritability accounts for upwards of
Nghiên cứu các cặp sịnh đôi trong lịch sử chỉ ra rằng sự di truyền
30-40% of the variance in the development of anxiety disorders (Hettema et al., 2001).
chiếm 30-40% sự chênh lệch trong việc phát triển các chứng rối loạn lo âu (Hettema et al., 2001).
Temperament – an innate rather than learned aspect of personality – has been found to
Tính khí - một phần di truyền chứ không phải học hỏi của tính cách - được cho là
be important in the development of anxiety disorders.
có tác động lớn đến sự phát triển của rối loạn lo âu
In particular, the temperamental quality of behavioural inhibition––characterised
Đặc biệt, bản chất bẩm sinh của việc kiểm soát hành vi - thể hiện qua
by shyness, fear of unfamiliar situations and withdrawal––has been identified as
sự ngại ngùng, sợ hãi các tình huống bất thường và sự rút lui - luôn được coi là
an important risk factor.
một yếu tố rủi ro
(REF: Svihra &amp; Katzman, 2004; Behavioural inhibition: A predictor of anxiety.
(REF: Svihra &amp; Katzman, 2004; Behavioural inhibition: A predictor of anxiety.
Paediatr Child Health.
Paediatr Child Health.
2004 Oct; 9(8): 547–550.)
2004 Oct; 9(8): 547–550.)
Important environmental factors include exposure to potentially traumatic events, an accumulation
Yếu tố quan trọng về môi trường bao gồm sự tiếp xúc với các sự kiện có thể gây chấn thương
of stressful life events, and parenting behaviours, such as modelling and overprotection.
sự tích góp căng thẳng hàng ngày, và hành vi nuôi dạy rập khuôn và quá bảo vệ
(Ref: Rapee (2012).
(Ref: Rapee (2012).
Family factors in the development and management of anxiety disorders.
Gia đình góp phần cho sự phát triển và kiểm soát rối loạn lo âu
Clin Child Fam Psychol Rev. 2012 Mar;15(1):69-80.
Clin Child Fam Psychol Rev. 2012 Mar;15(1):69-80.
doi: 10.1007/s10567-011-0106-3.; Ref: Last et al., (1984).
doi: 10.1007/s10567-011-0106-3.; Ref: Last et al., (1984).
Precipitants of Agoraphobia: Role of Stressful Life Events.
Precipitants of Agoraphobia: Role of Stressful Life Events.
doi: 10.2466/pr0.1984.54.2.567 Psychol Rep April 1984 vol. 54 no.
doi: 10.2466/pr0.1984.54.2.567 Psychol Rep April 1984 vol. 54 no.
2 567-570)
2 567-570)
However, as we have seen with other categories of disorders, increasingly, there is a consensus
Tuy nhiên, như ta đã thấy ở các bệnh rối loạn khác, ngày càng nhiều người đồng ý rằng
that the best way of understanding how anxiety disorders develop is by considering the ways
cách tốt nhất để hiểu về sự phát triển của rối loạn lo âu là qua việc xem xét
in which biological risks may interact with environmental triggers.
sự tiếp xúc của các rủi ro sinh học với các kích thích môi trường